So tell me the story behind starting the
podcast.
>> Okay, the story behind the podcast. I
last week there was a guest in San
Francisco that was so worth interviewing
that it was a no-brainer for me. I
immediately booked a flight. I booked a
hotel. I booked studio time. But last
minute there was a scheduling mixup and
I was able to move everything but the
studio time which I had paid almost
$1,000 for. I didn't want to go to
waste. So, I texted my buddy Brandon and
asked him to show up to interview me.
And so, we turned this studio time into
an FAQ episode about the story behind
the podcast, some of the behind the
scenes, and also to share where it's
headed in the future. So, while this
wasn't the episode that I flew to San
Francisco to make, which by the way, I
think is the best episode that I've ever
produced, and I can't wait to share it
with you. Hopefully, it's interesting
for people who've been supporting my
little show since the beginning. So,
here's that FAQ episode.
>> We're rolling. Is that
>> Okay, cool. Yeah, we're we're good to
go.
>> So, Ryan, what's the story behind the
Peterman Pod and why'd you create it?
Okay, so the story behind the podcast,
it's honestly pretty straightforward,
which is that I know for a fact that
speaking well is a super high lever
skill for your career, for your
relationships,
pretty much anything in life. People are
going to perceive you better. You're
going to get more of the things you
want. And so I felt like, okay, how can
I become a better speaker? Well, I got
to practice more. In the past, the way
that I practiced was I'd went to this
thing called Toast Masters, which is you
get a speech and the speech gets graded.
And that's that's a great way to
practice public speaking, but it's uh
not that frequent. And also, at least
for me, I didn't reflect as hard on it
because it was just like the speech that
I'd give, I kind of come in and I got
all these other priorities. But I what
I've seen in content is that my ultimate
goal with the content is I want to put
out something that you really want to
listen to that's you know quality
quality stuff ideally and so I pour over
every word like in the editing because I
know that people are going to listen to
it and that is like a very powerful
commitment mechanism and it's also a
very powerful feedback loop because if
you gave speeches You could record it
and go through it, but what I found was
that I would record it these speeches
that I gave at Toastmasters, but I never
go through it because I just have all
these other things to do. But if I know
that I have to post it, then I'm really
going to pour over the the thing. And so
I thought, okay, I I want to create some
kind of video content. Podcasting feels
like the best way for me to kind of get
into it because I feel like I like to
talk about a little more professional
stuff. And so I thought, okay, let's
let's make a podcast. And I decided to
commit to a really lax goal because I
thought, okay, I'm already drowning in
responsibility and a bunch of other
things. And so I set a goal at the
beginning of the year. I want to make
one episode per month. And I in that
process, I learned that well, one the
the premise like I am getting a lot of
opportunity to practice public speaking
or just speaking in general. So, you
know, that was great. And I feel like
there's still so much room for
improvement. But the other thing I
learned is that it's actually so much
fun doing the podcast because what I
realized is that podcasting, if we do it
right, I'm just having a conversation
that I want to have here. Like, I just
wanted to talk to you about this thing.
And then as a byproduct, I'm getting all
this practice and all these things. And
you know, a lot of the other people I've
had on too, like are people that were
kind of dream people that I wanted to
talk to. So when I got to thinking about
a podcast, I thought, okay, what am I
going to talk about here? One of the
inspirations for this podcast comes from
something that came very early in my
career, which is that at Facebook there
are these career stories that these very
senior IC's write that details how their
careers grew, what are the things that
happened as they grew. At the time, I
really love those stories. Like I
remember I would just sit down and start
reading one and it's maybe a 50inute
read and I'd knock it out all at once
just really glued to the screen. Like I
love these career stories because
they're these super impressive people
that I looked up to. They had a ton of
interesting stuff that I was like
learning from and they're super engaging
stories because anyone at that level has
done a lot of you know interesting stuff
and all that. The thinking behind what
this podcast is is just bringing on
these super senior people and just
having them tell their career story. And
this is the thing that I'm already so
interested in hearing about that it
becomes a very natural interesting
conversation at least for me and
hopefully for the audience as well. So
that's kind of the story behind getting
into the podcast. I wanted to become a
better speaker and I think this is like
a very good mechanism for that. At the
same time, I want to share these super
senior IC stories or engineer stories
with the industry because I feel like
they're so inspiring and there's so much
to learn from them.
>> So, you've had a couple of your podcasts
really pop off. What are some of the
behind the scenes and surprising tidbits
from those episodes?
>> Yeah, so I think the first episode that
really did well was the Philips Sue one.
He's a super senior engineer whose
writing was very famous within meta and
but otherwise he's not super wellknown.
He speaks very well. He has all these
interesting stories from you know people
who grow to a distinguished engineer.
There's all the stuff that they did to
do really impressive work and he shared
all of that. You know some of the behind
the scenes. I think one thing that I
remember distinctly is when I was
recording that episode, the energy
during the conversation was really
really different. Like when I was
listening, I felt like I was just so
enamored while he was speaking. Like
while he was speaking, I just I felt
like I was just fully zoned in and I was
almost addicted to the conversation
while was happening live. it sounded uh
so interesting and so you know I was
super happy about it after I recorded
it. Um and I put a lot of work into
editing it because he was someone that I
always looked up to. But yeah, I
remember after I posted it like just in
a day or two I I the the graphs were all
going vertical. But I think the thing
that was
I think special about that was that it
showed to me that it's not just me that
likes these stories that I I love these
stories, but I think other people also
really enjoy it and this can be, you
know, kind of product market fit for the
podcast. I think one episode where I
felt a similar energy with that Philip
one was the recent episode with Ethan
Evans. But the thing that really
impressed me was that Ethan speaks so
well. Honestly, I think he's like one of
the best speakers that I've seen in
tech. Like during the conversation, I
was I felt that energy again where I was
just during the conversation I couldn't
stop listening to him. It was so good. I
think the thing that's different between
that one and the Philip episode is the
trailer edit is kind of ridiculous. Like
I don't know, Acquired and uh Lex and a
lot of those guys. I mean, they're so
well recognized at this point that the
hook, like the thing that gets you to
listen is that you know that it's going
to be good because it's acquired or that
it's Lex or whatever. They don't need to
bring you in. But for someone like me
that's pretty new, you know, if I just
go straight into the conversation, a lot
of people are going to just click off.
So, I've been putting together these
trailers that are like, "Hey, this is,
you know, this is the reason why you
should listen. Like, here are the
absolute snappiest attentiongrabbing
bits that you should listen for." And um
when Tino, my video editor, when he put
together that trailer and I watched it
the first time, I was just like, that is
ridiculous. That is so good. It it is so
insane. That that edit is it's almost
too much. It's it's like super
aggressive. The video starts out it's
like, you know, this is the most
brutally honest. Like it's just like
crazy uh attentiongrabbing energy. By
the way, quick aside here. People have
given me a lot of great feedback in the
YouTube comments. I really appreciate it
and listen to all of them. I'm trying to
strike a balance between grabbing the
attention and also not going too
overboard. One idea that I have which I
think will also make the content a
better listen is in places where there
are more recurring listeners. So that
means Spotify, Apple Podcast, wherever
you get your podcasts. I'm thinking of
doing no trailers or maybe a very easy
to listen to quick one that just has one
or two lines. And so if you don't like
the trailers, I'd recommend you listen
there. It'll be nicer for recurring
listeners. But on YouTube, I still think
there's a lot of value in putting a
trailer that wins over someone that's
new to the show. So, I'll still be
putting effort into those. I'll just try
to keep them a little bit more tasteful
and not go overboard. So, keep me
honest. You can drop comments on
YouTube. I'll take a look at them and we
can kind of figure out a good balance as
we go. And now back to the show. I was
so excited when I saw that trailer. I
was like, we got to we got to shift
this. I it had that like energy during
the conversation and I feel like the
trailer was probably my favorite trailer
so far. And yeah, so far it's doing
quite well. So pretty happy about that.
>> So after all of those previous guests,
who are some of the future guests that
you would love to have on your show? So,
when you think about this podcast, like
my my dream guest list is very different
from a lot of other tech podcasts
because I want to find these hidden
super senior engineers who they're no
one knows them at all. They're just
really incredible on their team, in
their org, and they went up like crazy
at, I don't know, Google, Facebook,
wherever. And they're super wellknown
there. So, they have done so many really
impressive things to get where they are.
They have incredible stories and they're
engineers that we can all look up to,
but you've probably never heard of them.
And so, how do you find this list of
people? It's actually really tough cuz I
LinkedIn search is like pretty bad. Um,
these people are not super active
typically as well um on social media or
wherever. You can't just Google for this
list of people. And so I've gotten lucky
because I work in big tech and so I can
source some of these candidates and I
think a lot of the early candidates were
just using my network and the people
that I really look up to and I think are
incredible engineers. But past that,
actually, the way that I've been
building this list is by asking the
audience, who is that senior IC that is
in your org that you're super impressed
by that you want me to interview? And
that has worked super well. I've reached
out to a ton of people now. There's a
bunch of people from other companies
like Apple, Google, Microsoft that I'm
planning on interviewing. And that was
only possible because someone in the
comments on YouTube said, "This guy is a
super strong engineer. Please interview
him." And that's kind of how I've been
building list so far.
>> So, you've been podcasting for a while.
What's one of the hardest things you've
learned about podcasting that you didn't
know until you started doing it? The
thing that I didn't realize until I
started podcasting that is very
different from normal conversation, and
I'm still getting better at this, is
that when we're we're trying to produce
this audio file that sounds good to
people and have a good conversation, but
it's very natural when you're speaking
to someone to verbally acknowledge what
they're saying, right? You're you're
saying things like, "Uh-huh. Uh-huh."
Right. Yeah. Mhm. Right. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. And if you do that while the
guest is speaking, you can just imagine
someone in your AirPods, you're trying
to listen to someone and all you can
hear is the Uh-huh. Uh-huh. Right. Yeah.
Mhm. Mhm. And so I've been working on
that where uh it's very different from
normal conversation in that when you're
speaking or when the guest is speaking,
I'm just nodding vigorously and trying
to hold myself back from saying
anything. Uh, I think that's probably
the biggest thing that's different.
>> So, you work a full-time job and you
create content on the side. How do you
balance the two?
>> I think it's it's very difficult. Um,
especially with big tech being a little
more intense these days where you to
meet expectations, you already have to
work a lot. So, then doing this
extracurricular stuff is going to push
out something in my life. And you know,
for me, every Thursday for about two
years, I was staying up till, I don't
know, 4 a.m. writing a newsletter
because I had to wait till the last
minute because I was just struggling to
stay afloat on that. And yeah, I
remember once I I was grabbing lunch
with um Gerge, who writes a really um
the largest uh engineering newsletter
and when we were catching up over lunch,
he said he was surprised that I was
working at the same time as as doing the
newsletter. And I totally understand why
because he said something like, you
know, be careful about burning the
candle at at both ends. And you know,
after having experienced this for the
last two or three years, he's totally
right. It's um definitely a lot of work
and I think you know if I had a family
or uh other time commitments I think
like I would I would literally be
drowning. Thanks for listening to the
podcast. I don't sell anything or do
sponsorships but if you want to help out
with the podcast you can support by
engaging with the content on YouTube or
on Spotify if you want to drop a review.
That'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to